Take a minute. The meeting has now
started and I am admitting everyone.
Good morning everybody. Uh this is
Dominic Zerlo with the New Mexico
Department of Health Center for Medical
Cannabis and Psilocybin. Um we are going
through and admitting everybody into the
meeting. It does take a minute or so for
everybody all to get in the meeting. In
the meantime, I will uh just like to
remind everyone we are recording this
meeting. Uh and we do post the meeting
on the website. So we do also ask that
people ensure they are using appropriate
language. Um it is also why other than
some of the department of health and
members and the board members, we do not
have everybody on camera and that is
twofold. one to ensure that individuals
who are in areas of the state where they
do not necessarily have uh the best
internet that they can stay on as much
as possible and when we have lots of
video on it that unfortunately uh
creates too much bandwidth it usage and
people tend to drop off more often than
they sometimes already do unfortunately.
Um and so the other reason is just to
ensure that there is nothing in the
backgrounds that we cannot actually post
up uh as part of the live recording. Um
while that has happened in the past in
some other meetings, thankfully not for
this board or its committees, it has
happened at other times and we want to
ensure that this meeting is as public as
is possible. And so just have those as
the reminders. For those who are still
just joining, my name is Dominic Zerlo
and I'm with the New Mexico Department
of Health Center for Medical Cannabis
and Psilocybin. And this is the medical
psilocybin advisory board meeting for
February 27th. And at with that, I will
turn it on over to the chair, Ian Dunn.
Ian, uh, the meeting is
>> Morning everyone.
>> Good morning, everyone. Thank you so
much for joining. Um, I really
appreciate all of your time. Um, so I
will call the medical psilocybin
advisory board meeting to order at 9:03
a.m. and I'm really glad to see you guys
here. So, first things first, can I have
the department pull up the PowerPoint?
>> Uh, in process right now.
>> Perfect.
>> All righty. And then if you want to go
ahead and go to the agenda. Perfect.
Already on it. Um, so again, welcome
everyone. My name is Ian Dunn. I'm a
nursing and psychology student as well
as a mental health advocate and the
chair of the medical psilocybin advisory
board. Um, and since it has been since
December since we heard the original
introductions of our other members, I'm
going to go ahead and turn it over to
them to just give us a reminder on who
they are and why they're here.
>> So, I'll go down the list just
alphabetically. Uh, Brenda
Burgard.
>> Hello everyone. Thank you for having me.
I'm Brenda Burgard and I am uh chairing
the training and education for the
medical psilocybin. I am a mental health
practitioner and um I'm also president
of DRIM for New Mexico.
Okay.
>> Uh Chris Piscus.
>> Morning everyone. I'm Chris Piscus. I'm
a chairman of the propagation committee
and a veteran and a advocate and
ambassador with the Royal Cars Project.
>> Thank you, Chris. Alana Dances.
>> Hi everyone. I'm Alana Dances. I am the
Medicaid director. Uh before this, I was
the chief medical officer of Medicaid
and I'm a a nurse practitioner, um a
practicing nurse practitioner, a primary
care provider. Thanks,
Thank you, Alana. Desba
Desbar, um the chair of the equity,
access, and cultural considerations
committee. Um and I'm here in Santa Fe.
>> Thank you, Desbot. Uh Larry Leman.
>> Yeah, good morning. Larry Leman. I'm the
chair of the end of life committee. I'm
a um Emily addiction medicine physician
and psychedelic researcher and therapist
at UNM. Good to see everybody.
>> Thank you, Larry. And Ian, I believe
that is everybody on the board that is
present at this time.
>> All righty. Well, the agenda is on the
screen. Do we have a motion to adopt it?
>> A motion to adopt.
>> Any second?
>> A second.
>> Second.
>> Second. Perfect. All righty. And then I
will Any objections to adoption of the
agenda?
Without ad without objection, the agenda
is adopted.
So now I'm going to go ahead and turn
over to the
Department of Health to see if there are
any updates from the program.
>> Thank you, Ian. And first I'd like to uh
make sure that we introduce our staff as
well. And so I'll go through uh that
list. So uh and again for those who may
have missed in the very beginning as the
meeting was starting my name is uh
Dominic Zerlo and I am the director for
our center. Uh so with that can we go to
Brenda?
>> Good morning everyone. Uh Brenda
Martinez that's okay.
I'm the deputy director here at the
center for medical cannabis and
psilocybin.
>> Thank you, Brenda. Uh Johnny.
>> Yeah, morning. My name is Johnny Musher
and I'm a management analyst.
>> Rob,
>> good morning. I'm Robert Shuckner. I'm
the medical director for the program.
>> Jorge.
>> Good morning everyone. I am the medical
psilocybin program manager Gonzalez here
in Albuquerque.
>> Raymond,
>> hello everyone. Can you hear me?
>> Yes.
>> Awesome. Raymond Gigos. I am the data
and systems uh analyst for the program.
>> Thank you Raymond. Adrian,
>> hi buenos. My name is Adrian Espa and
I'm a health educator for the department
of health cannabis and suicide program.
>> Thank you Adrian. Katie.
>> Hey good morning. My name is Katie Fry
Tag. I'm a health educator with the
program.
>> Thank you Katie. Carmen.
>> Good morning everybody. Carmen Batista.
I'm a health educator with the program.
>> Thank you Carmen. Ismael.
>> Good morning everybody. My name is
Ismael Zut and I'm one of the health
educators here in the program.
>> Kathy.
>> Morning everyone. I'm Kathy Ager. I'm
project manager.
>> Thank you. Thank you Kathy. Uh Chris
Woodward.
>> Hi everybody. Um I'm Chris Woodward. I'm
deputy general counsel for the
department of health and I'm the
attorney who represents the medical
cannabis and psilocybin program.
Thank you, Chris. And I that is all at
this point in time. And so with uh with
regard to our introductions and so Oh,
and pardon me. Actually, we do have one
other individual. Uh Miranda, would you
mind introducing yourself?
>> Hi, good morning. I'm Miranda Durham,
the chief medical officer for the
Department of Health.
>> Thank you, Miranda. I didn't see you
sneak in there for a moment, but thank
you for joining. having some tech issues
this morning. So, thank you.
>> Well, welcome for welcome to the
meeting. Um, and so with that, what um I
would just like to go ahead and do is um
as far as an update for the program, the
program has been of course continuing to
support all of the various committees
for the board and the board and starting
to work on translating uh some of the
work that has been done into the
potential uh regulations. Um and that of
course is what primary purpose of
today's meeting is going to be looking
at propagation and we'll be looking at
that outline um to be able to see uh how
that moves forward. Um and then we'll of
course adapt from the decisions that are
made here in the board. Um and then the
other thing I just wanted to let
everybody know is that we have been very
successful in our hiring and we actually
have two new staff members who will be
joining specifically on the psilocybin
side. As many of you may have noticed,
we had a lot of people from the
department who are joining on in and who
are supporting us. And most of those
individuals have other positions and
work that they're doing, especially with
regard to the medical cannabis side of
the program. And so, right now, the only
staff member that we actually have who
has been dedicated solely to psilocybin
has been Jorge Gonzalez, our uh program
manager for the program. But starting on
Monday, we do have Leslie Peterson who
will be our senior um uh compliance
officer position. Uh and she will be
starting as I mentioned on Monday. And
then in two weeks we will have our
assistant environmental scientist who
will be starting uh whose name is Cyrus
uh Rasmusen. Um and so he will be
starting here in a couple of weeks. So
that will really help us to be able to
move things forward and to still meet
the timelines that we have talked about
previously with regard to uh having the
first patients by December of 2026.
Um which is by the way only 10 months
away. So we have a lot of work that's
going on but that's essentially what has
been happening with regard to the
program side. uh we've been working
diligently again with this and I just
want to make sure before we start going
into all the other details and the
updates from the various committees. I I
just want to say what a pleasure it
actually has been in or to be able to
work with the different committees and
the amount of work that each of the
committees is already doing. And so not
just the board members who are chairing
those various committees but all the
members of the public of uh the future
industry and the future providers who
have been joining in and really
providing such great feedback with
regard to how things are progressing and
with regard to what they would like to
see, how they would see it and how we
can continue to reach out. Now, we do
know because we've had limited uh staff
members so far. Um but as you can see,
we are trying to do this with as many
people coming in from different areas as
possible. And so we'll continue having
the meetings. We are working on some in
person. In fact, uh one of the
committees um actually two of the
committees I believe are in the process
or have already set up some in-person
meetings. And so just as a reminder uh
to see all of the meetings that are
coming on up, if you go to our main
website, and we'll put that in the chat
in just a minute, you can actually go
there and see the list of the meetings
uh in in date order of when they're
going to occur and how to join those.
So, um with that, I will turn it back on
over to you, uh Ian, uh for our next
set.
>> Uh yeah. So I will actually go ahead and
also turn over to Chris. His committee
has been working on or not quite yet.
Sorry about that. Let's hear an update
from each of the chairs of the
committees. Um and then we can go ahead
and
work on propagation.
Uh if you could roll call the chairs.
Thank you.
>> Sure. Uh so uh one again I'm going to go
down through the list of how they are on
the system uh right here just because
it's easiest. So Brenda, would you like
to give an update for your committee?
>> Uh yes, I haven't had much of an up
update since um the first um meeting
because my next meeting is next Friday.
Um, however, it looks like we did do um
a lot of work in that first meeting and
um the
uh document was posted up there and then
um it there wasn't really much to do on
there. We had really good input uh uh
from the get-go. It was like, you know,
um uh really good um ideas and uh
comments that were given in that first
meeting. So, the second meeting, um, I
would just like to go over some of those
things just to with a fine tooth comb
and see if there's anything else that
anybody would like to comment or add to
the document if at all possible. Um,
anything new happening uh with um
psilocybin in the news or anything like
that? Um, so um all are welcome in the
next meeting for training and education.
Thank you.
>> Thank you, Brenda. Then we will uh go
next to Desba. Desba, do you mind
providing an update?
>> Hi. Yes. So, we've had uh three
meetings, four meetings. I'm sorry, I
lost count. Um mostly just because I'm
trying to like make sure that I'm
targeting different part uh parts of the
uh community. Those who are like working
in the evenings and those who are
working during the day. I wanted to make
sure that we have access to everybody.
Um I definitely would like to see more
diversity of comp of people in the
committees. Um I uh really appreciate
everyone's time who has come and
attended and given their input. Um,
generally speaking, a lot of what I've
been hearing is, you know, anything
from, um, incarcerated individuals, um,
you know, as far as like the equity act,
uh, point of view, is incarcerated
individuals, um, financial Medicaid, um,
concerned, how we're going to be using
the equity fund, um, that has been
passed through the legislation, which
I'm hoping at some point we can get to.
Um but then also just hearing about uh
from other people in other parts of this
of the country in Oregon, Denver, what
their um
uh experience has been, whether it's
been on the um behind the scenes uh
propagation or facilitation side of you
side. Um and then also what that uh
access is on the um patient side um and
what that can look like. And just to
reiterate that that we are still kind of
holding a little to have input from
Native Nations um and what that would
look like. We were waiting for the
legislative session to end which was
just a few days ago. Um, so hopefully
we're going to be able to get the tribal
liaison involved um with more community
outreach and hopefully we can schedule
some more in-person um input and really
just kind of move forward with what that
looks like for the communities because
it is not just um cultural
consideration, it is also rural um in
different parts of New Mexico. We are
one of the largest states um but then
also what it looks like specifically for
our people here, the ancestral wisdom.
Um, so I'm really looking forward to
even more input, but it sounds like we
have quite a variety of different um I
don't want to say agendas, but just
concerns um from the different sectors,
whether it's on the patient side, how
that equity and access and cultural
considerations is going to look like and
then also on the the um I don't know the
facilitator propagation side and what
that's going to look like with equity
and access for them paying for training
Um and so equity, access, cultural
considerations has a lot of intersection
with the other committees. And so um
trying to make sure that we um create
that framework that it's it it is
supporting all of the other committees
as they move along and as we have those
considerations moving forward.
>> Thank you, Desba. Um, and then the next
committee, um, is going to be Larry
Leman. Larry, I'm bringing your slides
up now. Give me just a moment.
Okay. And the slides are should be
showing at this time. We'll give it
There we go.
>> Great. Thanks, everybody. Good to good
to see everybody here. Um, we've had
three meetings so far. are um these are
the scopes and responsibilities that we
established and we're kind of gradually
working through um uh through each of
these. A lot of the focus of the last
few meetings and I'll give a little
update in the next slide is has been
looking at like how is the care going to
be provided? Um what are the role of um
therapists? What are the role of
spiritual team members, chaplain um end
of life end of life das um you can go to
the next slide.
So um our first meeting was you know was
basically just just to organize. Then we
decided that we really needed to do some
self-education and get ourselves all on
the same page. So on January 22nd Chris
Caldwell uh founder of ELLL psychedelic
care came and talked gave an amazing
talk. Um then just last week Jen Clement
um who's also a psychedelic chaplain um
gave a talk on the role of spiritual
care. had really good discussion with
both of those. Um I'd encourage people
who are um interested to you know when
they're posted there's a little delay in
getting them posted for instance the
Jen's talk is not up to look at those
talks I mean I think people have found
them really really helpful and then we
have a few more coming up March 20th
death doula presentation James Brown
who's a RMD on pharmacological issues
we're looking at some other potential
areas though to get more information
hospice related issues indigenous
perspectives home care. And our our
current goal is to try by May to have a
blended uh in-person virtual meeting um
where we can um actually have like a
little more of a conversation while
still preserving access to people um
online. And then I we'll sort of head
into making more specific
recommendations on um on each of the
each of the items. But I would encourage
people on the committee if you get a
chance to to look at some of the
meetings you at least to watch the
presentations.
>> Thanks everybody.
>> Thank you Larry. And for those who if
for any reason you can't see the slides,
I have put those the information on them
in the chat so you can also see uh the
list of guest educators that are
planned.
Uh okay. And so then uh Ian if you don't
mind I'll go to you and we'll leave uh
Chris with propagation for last. So Ian
>> yeah so the dose administration and
clinical practice committee we've done a
lot of good work in hearing from
pharmacists providers and others on how
to properly dose it especially when
we're taking into account the fact that
we're working with biomass and not um
synthetic chemicals. So I think the
discussion around it has been really
good. um nothing formalized yet, just
working on getting the numbers in
agreement and how to work with biomass
on that side. In regards to the patient
qualification and safety committee,
we've adopted a uh clinical support tier
system where patients that would have
other coorbidities who may need more
clinical support when receiving
psilocybin treatment um have access to
that. That could include um risk
mitigation. That can include um
stabilization and other factors to
ensure that when they are um using
medical psilocybin they are in a safe
space physiologically
and um we are currently working on what
conditions warrant what clinical
support. So it's been a really good
discussion.
>> Thank you Ian. Um and so then at this
time uh we will move to um Chris Pascus
with uh just a general overview with
regard to propagation and then Chris
when you are ready I will display the
outline.
>> Thank you Dominic. I think you can
probably start pulling it up. Um the
propagation committee has meetings I
believe and we've had a a range of
attendance from 10 to 30 attendees plus
program staff. And so it's been just a
really successful
um
community
uh proposal that we're making for our
first draft recommendations. And I I
just am super grateful for all the
people that have dedicated so much time
to that process. And I know many of you
are here today in this meeting. And so I
want to thank you all. And um
yeah, basically like I said, this is uh
the first draft propagation framework.
And I'm assuming you have it up,
Dominic, although I still can't see it
on the screen.
>> Yeah, I do. And I'm also going to put
section by section as we go through them
into the chat. So, um I'll start with
the first section. Uh which is purpose
and scope. Um would you like me to read
through them, Chris?
>> Um yeah, and
I guess I have a question for Ian, too.
Are we just going to go through this
section by section and pause for a
comment on each one?
So, I'm going to treat it like you're
the sponsor of the recommendation. So,
um he'll read a section and then you can
kind of give your thought process behind
um why you support that piece of
regulatory
language. Um and then we can talk about
it as a group.
>> Does that sound good?
>> Yeah. I wouldn't say this is in
regulatory language though uh at this
point. It's all pretty plain language
and from my understanding as this goes
through the process the department of
health will put this into regulatory
language. Is that correct?
>> Yes, that is correct Chris. And so what
you're seeing here is really that
framework and the outline uh for it. And
then the department will take this and
actually convert it over into the the
regulatory details and language uh and
uh uh make sure that it's actually uh
correct with regard to the spirit and
intent.
>> Okay.
>> Excellent.
>> With that then uh so this first per
portion is purpose and scope. Establish
a regulated framework for the lawful
propagation, production, testing, and
preparation of psilocybin products in
New Mexico. Emphasize public health,
safety, consistency, and traceability.
Minimize duplication by utilizing
existing state, county, and municipal
licensing and inspection authorities.
All right, so this is the bare basics.
It's just telling us, you know, what
we're doing. Uh essentially the
propagation committee looked at
everything from growing the mushrooms to
getting them into the hands of
facilitators and and came up with this
first draft uh going into this meeting.
So any thoughts on section one?
>> All right, Dominic, will you read
section two, please?
>> Absolutely. Section two, authorized
species. Whole mushroom fruing bodies
shall be harvested for use in this
program. Mycelial biomass products are
prohibited.
Um, so after lengthy discussion in
committee and I reached out to people in
Oregon and Colorado to kind of get an
idea of why they chose the species they
did for their programs. Um we decided to
not limit
the the species for this program and uh
but we are limiting it to whole mushroom
fruing bodies uh restricting the use of
my biomass and I can kind of get more
detailed if anybody would like on that.
>> Um this is Miranda. I don't know if it's
inappropriate to ask now, but if you
could just explain what myelial biomass
products are or
you know at some point will there be uh
definitions in
>> so
>> in the document
>> uh I'm sure the the micologists are
going to tear me up on this for
describing it the way I am but
essentially the the fruing body is the
mushroom what we know of right and then
the mcal biomass would be like the roots
kind of and so that it is the substrate
with the uh the mycelial network
um
>> got it
>> included in that.
>> Thank you.
>> Yes.
Are there any other questions on why we
decided to
um not limit the species?
And again, I don't want to torture
everyone who probably knows this
already, but I I guess I mean this sort
of makes sense to me, but why when you
say why you made the decision, like what
are the reasons that you don't use myial
biomass versus whole mushroom?
>> So, it's hard to separate the mycelio
mass from the the substrate that you're
using. Um and and you can grow mushrooms
in a variety of substrates. We didn't
limit that. Um and so for example, you
could grow it in a substrate with, you
know, pasteurized manure. Um and then if
you're then taking that mycelio biomass
and putting it into some sort of
product, the it creates a lot more
testing issues. And um yes, that's why
we decided to to limit it to the fruing
body only for that those products.
>> Makes sense. Thank you.
>> Yeah. And if I could piggy back off of
that, it it's the difference between
like harvesting
a spear of green onion versus just
harvesting the roots. Whatever the roots
are in, it's gonna like you said, you
said the we were gonna tear you apart.
You described my celio biomass very
well. Um,
but yeah, it's basically the root. So,
you're going to pull up a lot of if it
was, let's say, dirt or if it was manure
or if it was whatever, it's going to end
up contaminating.
Got it. Thank you.
>> And just to add on to that and you you
you can see this um in the the myelial
advertising war between rise mushrooms
and all kinds of other stuff that oh our
product has you know fruing bodies
versus what could be uh misconstrued as
helpful and beneficial. So it's also
just you know you get more bang for your
buck I guess essentially. Um it's act
the medicine is in the in the um whole
fruitruing bodies.
It could it could um not not just the
contamination, but it could
uh
it just it interferes with the the I
guess the
the medicine,
not not the medicine itself, but it
interferes with the weight of like what
is the actual medicine in the fruing
body versus like you're getting mostly
Thank you.
>> Any other questions about how we about
section two?
>> All right. Um can you move on to section
three, Dominic, please?
>> Uh yes indeed. So permit structure there
are actually different parts with this.
So I'm doing uh permit structure A. Um
and uh this starts with permits issued
by the department required for
production which includes cultivation,
harvesting, processing for example
homogenizing and packaging and applying
persons can apply for one or any aspect
of the permit. Demonstrate psilocybin
containing mushrooms. Products are kept
in secure location. And just as some
examples of how locations could be
secured would be with double locks,
video surveillance, alarm system,
commercial grade locks, keypad entry,
and other types of security issues.
There was just a a question or a note
that had been made about uh making the
language a little tighter. And then the
rem the reminder is just that this is
the outline and the language in the
rules themselves will be uh a little bit
more specific and cleaner so to speak.
Um and so we have that aspect and so
again this is the permits issued by the
department required for those aspects of
production. Um and then that they have
to ensure that items are kept secure.
Right? I think this section is pretty
straightforward. um this permitting
process will not require you know
multiple layers of paperwork if people
are doing you know multiple things
within this process. So it'll be like a
a checkbox system. So if you're
cultivating obviously you're probably
going to be harvesting and then um
processing or packaging in some way. And
so you would just click the additional
uh
additional production uh permits that
you need and permitting would not be
there would not be an additional fee for
permitting which Colorado has run into
some significant issues with the high uh
I think they do licenses up there so
licensing fees and uh yeah so there will
be no permit ing fees. There will
probably be inspection fees or other
things as required through um the the
process, but no permits permitting fees.
Any questions on section A of or yes,
subsection A of section three.
>> Yeah. So, um
I was just curious about the
separation of cultivation and harvesting
just because I'm afraid of someone
applying for like a cultivation license
and then not being able to harvest
because they're distinct. That wouldn't
happen. I saw Dominic said
>> and those are just the different aspects
that are included within production.
It's not necessarily that someone's
going to say, "Oh, we're going to
cultivate and then but we're not going
to harvest." So, that's just out
outlining that they're all there. Uh, if
that makes sense.
>> So, those are activities, not specific
licenses.
>> Correct. Correct.
>> Okay. Cool. That's perfect for me.
>> All right. If there's no further
comments, let's go to subsection B.
Uh now, uh here with subsection B, um
Chris, I'm not including in the text yet
the sunset clause. I figure we'll tackle
that separate.
Uh so with this subsection B business
facility and occupancy compliance, proof
of ownership of the land facility or
written approval from the owner, for
example, lease specifying use to include
psilocybin cultivation or production,
business license in the state of New
Mexico, proof of registration with New
Mexico Secretary of State, registration
with New Mexico tax and revenue, local
building and safety authorities such as
certificate of occupancy, fire code
compliance, electrical and HVAC
inspection and uh just as a note, no new
psilocybin specific building standards
unless explicitly necessary. And just to
sort of comment on all of that um
together with regard to the local
building and safety authorities, those
can actually be different in different
municipalities and counties. And that's
why we are just ensuring that uh anybody
who is applying for a permit understands
and realizes that depending where in the
state they are, they may have some other
local uh permits or licenses that they
need to acquire. But we're not as a
department not imposing additional ones
upon them.
Okay, this is all pretty much boiler
boilerplate stuff to do business in the
state of New Mexico already. We didn't
really add anything in there. Um, we
tried to keep regulatory restrictions on
cultivators as minimal as possible to um
to allow them to operate as freely as
they can and to um be profitable.
And you'll see later on we we put some
safety guard rails in place u at the
next level. Any questions on this
section? Um
and we will come back to the when do you
want to come back to the sunset pause?
At the end, Dominic
>> Yeah, I would suggest we do that at the
end.
>> Okay.
And then I also would like to
potentially bookmark a spot for
predatory financing uh language.
Is that going to come out with the next
draft, do you think, Dominic, or are we
going to
>> We actually have some language for that
that we can bring up. Uh and we can do
that together with the uh the residency.
Okay.
Any
questions on subsection B?
>> All right, let's move on to section C,
please.
So, with section C, zoning and municipal
municipal permits must be within the
geographical boundaries of New Mexico.
City and county planning and zoning
developments, land use approval,
conditional use permits where
applicable, for example, city of
Albuquerque raw food permit, food safety
training certification for employees,
and just as a note that local
governments retain uh zoning authority
consistent with existing agricultural,
light, industrial, and other
classifications. Uh basically this just
really kind of continues part of that
within uh from section B really just
talking about the fact that there may be
additional items that a permit uh or an
applicant may have to do with regard to
local zoning but then also adds in the
food safety because since this is a
product that is going to be ingested um
and as a medicine that uh food safety
processes should be followed.
Okay, I think this is pretty
straightforward. Um, does is there any
questions on subsection C?
>> All right, let's move on to subsection
D, please, Dominic.
>> And subsection D is agricultural. the
New Mexico Department of Agriculture
utilizing their pest and containment
mitigation guidance and that production
is treated analogously to controlled
environmental environment agriculture.
Again, I think this is pretty
straightforward. Are there any questions
on subsection D?
All right, let's move on to section
four, please.
>> So, section four is cultivation uh
standards. And please give me a moment
while I copy that into the chat.
Here we go. Um and then um here, oh my
apologies, I am scrolling in the wrong
direction. Uh uh so with regard to this
this is about growth medium that uh not
to restrict growth medium and all
substrates and inputs must be
documented, tracked and fully disclosed
on final product labeling. Uh this
actually references back to what Chris
was talking about earlier as far as the
growth medium could be different
products and we want to ensure that uh
that is listed within from a labeling
standpoint and documented. So for
example, one of and this was an example
that did come to us from Oregon where
the substrate utilized was a wheat
substrate and where an individual who
had celiac which is an intolerance to
gluten did end up having a reaction to
it. And so we want to ensure from an
allergen standpoint that all of that is
documented and tracked. Um and that's
just as an example. Um and then
environmental controls, indoor or
controlled environment cultivation
required, no pesticides utilized. Um and
uh there were there have been comments
with regard to including fungicides and
other chemical agents and other
substances determined harmful by the
department.
Um okay. So, as Dominic said, we just
want to make sure we're tracking what
substrates are used. So, that way if
people have sensitivities that we're not
um exposing them to something that they
don't, you know, um want, if people are
concerned about their mushrooms being
grown in manure, they can avoid those
products.
And, uh it's pretty standard and it it
almost necessary in New Mexico to grow
these things indoors. uh they just
aren't very prolific here. And
um yes, we want to keep So mushrooms are
concentrators and so we have to be
careful whatever we put into our
substrates or use around these things
because they will concentrate that into
the mycelial or into the fruing bodies.
And so that is why we expressly uh said
no pesticides and um
at some point want to have a banned
substance list uh
posted by the department of what you
cannot use in this space.
Any questions?
Yeah.
>> Yeah. Um I do have a question about the
fact that it says growth medium is not
restricted. I know that we have in in
section B they you point out that other
substances determined harmful by the
department um are taken out. But if
growth medium is not restricted does
that put us at risk of like if they do
use manure that puts them at higher risk
of E.coli coli and salmonella and does
that have any impact on what the
department is able to say for growth
medium?
>> I can answer that.
>> Oh Chris
>> uh in the specific case of you know if
it's grown in manure uh there will be
testing for E.coli coli and salmonella
as part of the testing protocols and so
that's uh one reason we decided not to
um restrict any kind of medium in this
space. Did you have something to add
Dominic? Yeah, I I was just going to say
that this is really just to say that
there we're not restricting growth
medium from a standpoint of, you know,
the basis of it, but if there are uh
individual components which end up being
potentially harmful, those can still be
banned at that point.
>> Thank you. Thank you.
Any other comments or concerns about
section 4?
Okay, let's go ahead and move on to
section five, please.
Okay. And so section five is harvesting,
processing, and homogenization.
Part A, batch definition, is a batch
defined as harvested and homogenized
under uniform conditions utilizing best
practices at no more than 1 kilogram
after drying over a 4-week period.
Batches must be fully homogenized prior
to testing. The homogenization
requirements section B. Physical
homogenization is required to ensure
consistent potency across the batch and
the purpose of this is for accurate
potency testing uh reduction and
reduction of dose variability.
>> All right. Excellent. So we and I think
we may need to look at the language a
little bit on here. It says this part
where it says 1 kilogram after drying
over a four-we period kind of sounds
like we have to dry it for four weeks.
Um but essentially what that's me
supposed to say is that they uh can
inoculate a group of containers and
um harvest anything you know in that
batch. A batch is considered anything
they harvest in that four-week period.
And so it can be in multiple
containers uh but basically the same
kind of inoculating conditions. And then
they are fully homogenized which means
they are the fruing bodies are harvested
and then ground up into a fine powder
and then that pow uh
uh
a small section of that powder will be
sent off for testing.
Uh, Disbon,
>> um, I'm just curious, would it help if
we had a wet versus dry language in
there? If that's what if if I'm
understanding your
uh,
sorry.
>> Yeah. Would would it help if you were
saying like at the point like the weight
is wet versus like when it's dry?
Because is that is that is that what
you're saying with the kilogram
that you're harvesting it wet at 1
kilogram or you or is it and then the
resultant is a kilogram when dry.
>> So the a batch will consist of 1
kilogram dried mushroom.
>> Okay.
>> Does that answer your question? And we
can't homogenize wet mushroom. It
>> Yeah, definitely what that would look
like.
>> I know. Well, I just wasn't sure if
there was like if that was part of the
issue was trying to decide what was the
1 kilogram at at the time of measurement
after a 4-week period. Sorry.
No worries. Did I answer your question,
Desba?
>> I'm going assume that's a yes. All
right, Ian.
>> Yeah. So, I just want to make sure I
understand it correctly. So if I'm a
producer, I can dry all of my mushrooms
and then I can just batch them into 1
kilogram and then that gets homogenized
and tested and all that.
>> Correct. But they all have to be the
same the basically the same inoculation.
So you have to they have to be on a
similar substrate because that has to be
tra track tracked
throughout the process and it uh it has
to be the same species of mushroom.
>> Well, thank you
Desbar.
>> Sorry, another question and I'm sure you
probably discussed this and I'm
apologize if it's so when we're defining
the batch versus a flush for a lot of
us. Some of us are
I think that might also be another
uh
>> I'm sorry Desbol. I feel like I keep
interrupting you. Are you
>> Oh, no, no, no. I'm just wondering like
when you're talking about a batch, I
mean I'm also new to this so I don't
understand fully, but like when you're
talking about a batch, are you also
talking about a flesh? because the flesh
is just like that one um harvest for
that one particular bin, right? So, is
that what you're talking about when
you're talking about a batch is that
just that one harvest from that one
particular point? Um
and all of you said inoculation, right?
So, all of these if you had like 10 tubs
or however and you harvest all of those
and then you weigh those and you dry
those, right? That's what you're talking
about when you're talking about a batch.
Yes. And so the the flushes is is when
you get multiple sets of mushrooms
coming off of a tub. So you you
inoculate a tub, you know, the
substrate, it it grows the mycelial
mass, it fruits, you harvest the fruit,
and then it'll often times grow a second
or even a third flush. And that's the
reason why we allowed for the four weeks
so that uh cultivators can
batch all three flushes attention.
>> Got it. Okay. All right. So that makes
sense. Thank you for clarifying that.
>> Yes. Um
is there any other questions on this
section?
And Chris, just so that you are aware,
uh it on the what I've actually done is
uh as this conversation has continued,
I've actually uh amended the language a
little bit just to specify this is for
fruing bodies from the same inoculation
which have been harvested over a 4-week
period
to clarify that aspect of it.
Yeah, I think that looks good. And then
I don't think we'll need to add the
substrate in there because that already
needs to be tracked. So, it's kind of
assumed that that each batch would have
to be on the same substrate.
>> Yeah, the substrates again would that'll
be tracked just as you said.
>> Okay. Excellent.
All right. Uh any other questions on
batching or why we why we did what we
did?
Excellent. Let's go on to section six,
please.
Okay. And just so everybody is aware for
this, this also has uh several sections.
So I'm going to do section A first. Um
and this is that uh regarding testing
and quality assurance. Testing authority
is performed by the department permitted
laboratories. Requirements for
laboratories to be permitted include
cannabis testing laboratories which have
been approved and have submitted their
uh standard operating procedures uh and
IDC's which is their and forgive me uh I
did not include it in here but it is
their um uh initial uh determination of
capability. It basically is uh making
sure that they actually have the ability
to perform the tests uh and the process
for extraction and similar pathway for
those who are not a cannabis testing
laboratory such as having ISO IEC uh or
NEAC NE A T NI um accredited laboratory
being being one of those two
accreditations or having those
accreditations and then again labs that
are approved or overseen by the
department which includes the state lab
division uh and especially with regard
the state lab division especially with
regard to uh potential testing and
verification of uh other laboratories
tests uh ensure proficiency and
verification testing annually and that
the department can require samples to be
conducted by additional tests for
validation purposes. That last one is
about um ensuring that for example if
one laboratory if there are concerns
that their tests may not be as accurate
as they should be uh then they could we
could request that they be tested by a
secondary lab to ensure that they are
testing in valid and appropriate ways.
>> Excellent. Thank you Dominic. Um yeah.
So basically this gives cultivators
three or uh laboratories kind of three
processes by which they can be um
validated
through either the the state lab
department or through these two other
verifying agencies ISO or NEAC.
Um and then
it it the proficiency and val
verification testing annually I think is
very important. So what that means is
like every year um we'll provide a or
all the labs will get like a uh
homogenized sample of some sort and they
have to like you know hopefully come in
with within some standard deviation of
each other on on the
um potency and other uh verification
results.
Are there any questions on the testing
authority?
Okay, Chris, I don't see any questions
on the testing authority. There is a a
question that did come in in the chat
when I was reading that portion um
asking if a cultivator grows two
different as an example two different
strains uses two different substrates
they would need to send in four samples
for testing um and essentially yes it's
based upon the inoculation
uh based upon the this recommendation
and so yes if they were small different
substrates different uh different
inoculations then they would need to
send in the appropriate samples.
>> Yeah. Essentially, that would kind of
come down to the batching. And if you
grow on a different substrate, it's
going to be a different batch. If it's a
different strain, it's going to be a
different batch.
Any other questions?
>> All right, let's go ahead and go down to
section B, please. Subsection B. So this
next set is uh about testing uh the
required testing panels. Um and
essentially on this it is that testing
occurs once the batch is homogenized.
Cultivators must submit a sample of each
homogenized batch uh and maybe between 2
to 5 grams as required by testing
laboratory sampling procedures. And just
a note on that, that is recommendations
that we did get from labs that are
currently doing testing. As far as those
amounts, uh the product will need to be
retested um one year after the initial
test date. The department can require
additional tests if there are
complaints, concerns or in a random
process. No cultivated cultivation or
processing facility facility will be
asked to test more than four times a
year with regard to the random testing.
Uh this does not include if there are
contaminants or false statements made by
the organization facility or on the
labels. Potency testing would be uh
psilocin psilocybin including the three
analytes uh biocyin norcyin and
aruganasin.
Pardon me for my pronunciation.
Contaminant testing would include
microbial contaminants. These are just a
few examples including E.coli and
Salmonella. And heavy metals uh and
again this is an example would include
items such as arsenic, cadmium, lead and
mercury. Uh it would also include
testing for pesticides and fungicides
and synthetic tarpamine screening upon
request of the department in the event
there is a suspicion of it having been
added. Um and just as a note on that
that is just essentially we're looking
at synthetics are not uh to be used by
statute within this program uh for the
medical patients and so if that is added
in if there are synthetics added we
would have that screening if it is
suspected and then uh just a clause so
that the department can stagger the
implementation of testing as the
laboratories are permitted and are able
to provide validation of testing.
Excellent. Thank you, Dominic. Um, okay.
So, this is the most robust testing
profile out of any of the three states
that have a program so far. And I did
that for two reasons, or we kind of set
that up for two reasons.
Um, first, we want to make sure we're
giving a safe product. And we allowed
the cultivators a lot of room and not a
lot of regulation on how they can grow.
Um
and so
and second because both Oregon and
Colorado only have one operating lab
right now, right? And so by increasing
the amount of tests, not only are we
ensuring we're giving a safe product,
but we're also making it more
financially feasible to have more than
one lab, which I think is critical to
having a working program here in New
Mexico. Um, so
I'll open it up for questions.
>> And Chris, there is a question in the
chat from uh Larry Leman. Any rough
estimate on what the cost will be for
each batch analyzed? Um, and I can
answer that. Um, it if the entire uh
listing were to be implemented per
batch, it would cost somewhere between
about $600 to $1,000. But mind you,
those batches can be up to one kilogram,
which is a lot of doses.
So when you actually uh bring that
across the various dosing, depending on
what exactly ends up being with regard
to dosing, we're only talking a few
dollars per dose total.
>> Thank you, Dominic. Brenda,
>> do we know how much time it takes
between um uh harvesting and uh testing?
So, the the mushroom gets uh sent to the
lab. How long does it usually
uh take for testing? Do we know?
>> I can't answer that.
Go ahead, Dominic.
>> Yeah. So Brenda, it's going to depend on
various aspects such as drying. So how
long the drying time will take, which
will depend on what process the producer
themselves actually utilize. But from
the time of sampling, what the labs have
really told us is it's really only a
couple of days from when the lab
samples. So a lot of the the qu the
aspect of the timing is really going to
be on the producer side of how long
their processes take.
>> Thank you.
And that'll also be determined about
when they homogenize. So they have, you
know, a month to harvest all those
mushrooms, dry them, and then homogenize
them. And then whenever they send that
that test in is kind of that batch date
that gets applied to it at that point.
>> Other questions? Ian.
>> Yeah. So, with the synthetic tryptoamine
screening
um
and I could be wrong on this, is there
any way that we could have um limited
GMOs psilocybin? cuz that is an
regularly occurring tryptoamine, but it
would be synthesized in amounts greater
than what would be found in nature. Um,
is that any way
accounted for or does it need to be? I
don't think so, but I just wanted to
double check.
>> Oh, Chris, go ahead.
>> It's not something that came up in
committee
uh specifically. It's something I can
take back and look at in the next draft
if you want me to. But essentially if we
expect somebody is tampering with the
amount of um DMT or you know adding
something to a um
mushroom then we can do that synthetic
tryptoamine screening which pretty much
screens for everything in the there's a
database that's kept and uh I I think
they use massspec or something to um to
to weed out all kinds of different
compounds that can be added to these to
these substances. Go ahead, Dominic, if
you have something to add.
>> You you actually already said it, Chris,
and it it is the only thing I'd really
add is it's not something that from our
colleagues in both Colorado and Oregon,
they haven't really been seeing that as
an issue.
And it, you know, if if people want
synthetic tryptomines, they all they
have to do is go to the nearest head
shop and there's all kinds of funky
stuff in the chocolates and stuff there.
They're fine. So,
any other questions?
Okay. Uh and then the last section of
this and my apologies I just didn't copy
it in the last time round is uh just on
batch release. Um and really this is
just that all batches of course must
pass required testing before they can be
released for use.
Okay. All right. Let's move on to
section seven, please.
And section seven is uh food preparation
and product handling. Um and this is any
conversion of raw material into
ingestible or prepared products subject
to food safety oversight. For example,
environmental health food safety
divisions and the food safety and
handling training certification would
need to be required and no exemption
from those standard food safety
requirements.
And this alludes back to the portion up
above just requiring that um any anybody
who is applying for a permit ensures
that they go through the appropriate
food safety training and in this case
that they actually implement it and
utilize those processes.
>> All right, I think this section is also
um pretty straightforward. Um but any
questions?
>> Let's go to section 8 please.
>> So and section 8 does have a couple of
uh parts within it. And so the first
part this is all under labeling
packaging and traceability or the
tracking of products. So a packaging it
must be sealed labeled and ensure the
facilitator provides this information
for the label and the product
information for the patient. Uh and just
as a note the next couple of sections
actually have the elements of the label
and on an additional product information
document. Um because and just the reason
I say that is some of these are going to
be very small packages and um we don't
need receipts or labels on them that are
10 printed pages long. So uh we'll we
have that as a separate document,
but we'll get to that in a moment.
Any questions on section 8, subsection
8?
Let's move on to section B, please.
>> And section B is the label requirements
and the elements itself. Um the label
must be printed or affixed on the
product package and include um all the
required information in a legible font
at least eight points be in English
although it may also be provided in
other languages be unobstructed and
clearly visible and it will include the
producers's business name and permit
number. The type of product, for
example, homogenized fungi. Species and
cultivar name of the fungi. The net
quantity of contents using metric system
of measurement. Potency of psilocybin
analytes contained in the product
expressed in milligrams and calculated
using laboratory test results. Total
potential uh psilicin report. Uh and
this is where this is still being
determined in one of the other
committees whether it be um the total
potential psiloc psilocin or the total
psilocybin equivalent. Um and uh then
also the total psilocybin equivalent. Um
and then a logo designed and provided by
the department that notifies a
reasonable person the product contains
psilocybin no smaller than 1/2 x 1/2 in.
Unique identification of the product
lot. uh that will which is actually
entered into the state traceability
system that will be required. The
expiration date and the statement the
risk benefits drug interactions and
effects of psilocybin are not fully
understood. Individual results may vary.
The statement keep out of the reach of
children and the statement do not drive
a motor vehicle or operate machinery
while under the use of psilocybin.
And just as a note Eileen, thank you. I
I however am sorry that we won't be able
to help with the wallpapering um project
that you have with your uh very long
psilocybin labels that you were hoping
for. Thank you very much for injecting a
little humor.
All right. Uh so required label elements
I think most of them are pretty
straightforward.
Um,
are there any questions on how we kind
of came up with this?
Any issues anywhere?
>> All right, let's move.
Sir, was is there a comment?
>> Oh, I was just saying it looks great. 10
of 10. That section is beautiful.
>> Excellent. Let's move on to section C,
please.
Okay. And so, um, here this is the
product information document. And so
this would be a document available that
lists the following information in
English either in printed or electronic
document in 12point font or larger. And
again this would not be attached to the
product itself. It would be provided
secondarily. Um all of the requirements
for the product label would be included
on this so that they can be matched. A
statement regarding number of years the
business has been established in New
Mexico and a statement declaring the
state and county of residency including
length of time of the primary investors.
Results of all laboratory tests
conducted on the homogenized batch. Date
of homogenization.
Type and composition of the growth
medium used including type of grain,
soil, compost, pesticides and other
inputs. Um date of manufacturer or
processing of the final product. List of
all active and inactive ingredients in
descending order of predominance by
weight or volume. Growth medium used.
List of potential major food allergens
which might be contained in the product
or in the growth medium. Identify the
intended use and directions for use. A
description of how the product should be
stored. The following statement. This
product is not approved by the FDA to
treat, cure, or prevent any disease. The
FDA has not evaluated this product for
safety, effectiveness, and quality.
There may be long-term adverse health
effects from consumption of psilocybin,
including additional risk for women who
are or may become pregnant or are
breastfeeding. And the New Mexico Poison
and Drug Information Center phone. And
my apologies, the pesticides was uh
deleted. I accidentally had read it out
uh in here but that had been deleted
because pesticides are not allowed to be
utilized as mentioned earlier. So my
apologies on that.
Um and then the other uh one statement
and we'll actually bring this up a
little bit more uh when we talk as far
as the residency clause is just uh the
statement regarding the number of years
the business has been established in New
Mexico and it's a part of the larger
conversation. So, we'll hold on that.
But, um, regardless, we were planning on
including this on this particular
document simply because, uh, as we did
bring up, this seemed to be something
that committee members were in favor of
favor of regardless on the other
residency aspects. Um, with regard to it
that we'll discuss in a little bit.
>> I see Brenda has a question. Go ahead,
Brenda.
>> Um, I I don't know if I've missed this
or not. Is there an expiration date to
the the product here?
>> Yeah, that's actually on the label
itself. And then the document
information repeats everything on the
label.
>> Okay, thank you.
Oh, and there's a question uh in the
chat about adding suicide crisis
hotline, the 988 number.
I think that could be added without any
issue. Does anybody
that
>> I think that's a good idea.
>> Yeah. Okay, we will add that on in.
Thank you, Eileen.
>> And Ian, did you have a comment?
>> It totally slipped my mind. Sorry about
that.
>> No, thank you.
All right, I think uh let's move on to
section or subsection D rather.
>> Subsection D is about the traceability
or the tracking that we will do. Um and
this is uh utilize an online tracking
system as required by the department.
This would be end to end batch tracking
from cultivation through final product
steps for grow, harvest, processing,
testing, transport andor sale. and then
records defi retained for a defined
regulatory period for example five
years.
>> All right. So uh this would be pretty
much a basic tracking software just like
is used in the the cannabis industry. Um
people will or providers of that
software will be um
will have to provide the basic necessary
uh requirements for free and then they
can have add-ons for you know um
for other perks and and bells and
whistles in their software that you can
buy. Are there any questions about
traceability and tracking? Excellent.
Let's go on to section nine, compliance,
please.
>> Okay. And for compliance, the compliance
authority would be with the Department
of Health and then uh with regard to
only their applicable permits, the New
Mexico Department of Agriculture and
then local and building local building
and health department or inspectors with
regard to their local permits. There
would be clear corrective action
pathways prior to license suspension or
revocation. Um, and just sort of as an a
little bit of an explanation, for
example, say the department went in to
do an inspection of a facility. We
discovered um pesticides or mold or
other things that were growing um and
unsanitary conditions, then we would be
issuing for example a what is called a
notice of contemplative action. They
would have time to be able to correct
that. uh if they were not did not
correct it and upon reinspection then
what would occur is uh then the action
would be acted upon uh so whether that
be through permits being pulled or
suspended or through other means as
necessary um until they have actually
corrected the issues or the problems um
and then uh move forward with regard to
that. Also, there would be an appeal
process. Um, that is pretty standard and
it is actually something that we did
develop originally under the cannabis
program when the department of health
was actually um was regulating the
cannabis grow sections and cultivation.
And so we would be using similar
processes with regard to that which are
fairly standardized.
All right. Any
questions about compliance?
Excellent. Let's move on to
transportation, please.
>> Okay. transportation
um needs to be done and completed in a
safe and secure way that it ensure that
the uh contractors for example can meet
with others or allow for pickup so long
as there is a chain of custody form.
What we're talking about on this is that
either the producers or the
practitioners. So the the facilitators
would be able to transport as necessary
and needed to go between the production
and the um facilitation of uh psilocybin
being administered.
And another thing that this allows is it
allows um say a producer and a
facilitator to meet somewhere and u
arrange for a pickup in that location
being New Mexico being s such a vast
state. Um, that is one piece of feedback
I got from people in Colorado that
transportation costs were high due to
um, producers having to to drive long
distances and stay overnight, things
like that.
Any questions on transportation?
>> Okay.
Uh and then uh the last section as far
as uh for these types of items is the
future expansion and review. Um and this
really is just providing that this is a
framework that is designed to be
scalable. So as there are additional
laboratories, producers, facilities uh
that this would work with regard to that
um periodic review for scientific
developments, public health data and
operational performance. For example,
the idea as far as for the testing, if
there are additional potential
contaminants that start to come into
play, we would be able to add those kind
of items on in. Um, and uh there is a
question there in the chat uh relating
to the transportation uh from Mary Curry
uh specific regulations as a clinician
facilitator for transportation. uh Mary,
they would be the same um whether it be
um a producer or a uh facilitator, which
would include things such as making sure
that they're secure, safe, those sort of
things with regard to transportation.
Okay. And uh with regard to the future
expansion, I think that's really just
that we ensure that the regulations um
are actually open so that they can be
scalable. And I think as this outline
shows it, I I believe that they are
>> awesome. Uh any questions on section 11?
>> Okay, let's move on to section 12,
please.
>> And actually Chris, section 12 are the
definitions which we actually are
following some of the legal definitions,
some of which are in the statute and
moving forward. Um, so I would actually
uh ask and recommend that the
definitions not be adopted here. Just
simply that those will be a part of an
ongoing as the the various rules and
regulations for the different aspects
different definitions will kind of come
come to the for the front and some of
these may need to be amended as some of
those uh other sections are created.
>> All right, sounds good to me. Um, I
think,
uh, I'd like to give the board a chance
to go back and revisit any section or
subsection at this time. Um, having been
able to sit with it for a while. Uh, are
there any questions it about anything
that we've gone over?
>> Um, I don't have a question. I just I
will also side with um striking the
definitions. um if that is necessary.
>> I'm sorry, I might have missed. Why
would we strike the definitions?
>> Sorry, Alana. What we're going to be
doing is as the various regulations are
being done, the definitions are going to
be uh created through the department.
Some of them are actually statutory and
some of them may need to be amended as
other sections are created. And so we're
just asking that, you know, the
department be able to actually create
them and and uh to kind of go from
there. But we will look at and we are
utilizing some of the definitions that
have been provided. We are looking at
the ones from Oregon, from Colorado, uh
as well so that we can ensure that they
fit within our framework. Some of them
work very nicely. Some of them do not
because they use different language
within their statutes than we do, for
example.
Okay, that sounds reasonable. Thanks.
>> All right, that completes my uh
presentation of our first draft. I'll
turn it back over to you, Ian.
>> Uh if I may.
>> Yeah,
>> we we do still actually have the
residency. Would we like to go through
everything else first and then maybe
talk about the residency separately?
um that I'll leave that up to Ian.
>> Do you want me to go into that now?
>> Sure. Go ahead.
>> All right, let's go uh back to the
sunset clause information. So, right
now, and I I think we have Chris
Woodward here. He might want to jump in
on this. Um we unanimously passed a
recommendation for a sunset clause to
protect New Mexico residents. And uh
there is um
I'm trying to find this section right
now. I'm sorry.
>> That's okay. Uh it is on um
>> Oh, page two.
>> Sorry, Chris. Yes, page two has it.
>> H2.
Oh, there it is. Okay. Um would you like
to read the the sunset proposal Dominic?
>> Yeah. So the sunset proposal and this is
again to be considered by the board and
that initial ownership or sunset clause
from the committee. This is the language
that was originally utilized within the
committee. If the application is a
corporation, limited liability company,
partnership association, trust or other
legal or commercial entity. Ownership
requirements more than 51% of the
ownership interest in the applicant must
be held by one or more individuals who
have been residents of the state of New
Mexico for a minimum of 36 months
immediately preceding the date of the
application and B control requirements.
The individuals described
uh in subsection A must possess actual
authority to direct the management
policies and operations of the applicant
whether through voting rights,
management authority, contractual
rights, or other indicica of control as
determined by the New Mexico Department
of Health. Notwithstanding any other
provision of law and until January 1st,
2029, an applicant for a license subject
to this measure must demonstrate
compliance with the residency and
ownership requirements set forth in this
measure.
>> All right. So this was unanimously
uh accepted as a proposal um through our
committee and uh then there came into
some question whether this violated
interstate commerce laws. But after
talking with um consulting some some
other lawyers from the healing advocacy
fund and u another law firm um they say
that it cannot violate federal
interstate commerce laws because this
substance is federally illegal. So I'm
not sure where the Department of Health
lawyers stand at this point, but once
again this was a unanimously approved
recommendation.
Um,
and it, you know, we think it's
important to protect local co
cultivators. So, I would ask that the
the board um stand with us in approving
this as a recommendation and kind of
give the micology guild uh room to
continue um
debating that with the Department of
Health's legal team.
Any
questions on that,
Ian?
>> Yeah, I really like the idea of having
New Mexico interest represented first,
especially for those first three years
while the industry is taking off. My
biggest concern is that we are a medical
advisory board and this seems to be an
economic regulation.
So, I'm not sure if we have the
authority to economically regulate this
aspect of the program,
but I do really like supporting our
local businesses, and if this does turn
out to be possible, I would really uh
hope to vote for it.
>> I counter I disagree. I think the
economic feasibility is is inextricably
linked to the success of this program in
its entirety. So, I think we can make
recommendations on how the entire
program is set up. Um, that would be my
opinion. Uh, can we go to Chris
Woodward, please?
>> Hi. Um, so I'm Chris Woodward. I'm an
attorney with the Department of Health
and I had met with Chris and uh,
Victoria um, I'm sorry I'm forgetting
your last name and uh, some of the
program folks about this issue the other
day. Um
so uh first of all I do think that the
advisory board can make a recommendation
about this and you know I think that
that you can you can make a
recommendation about a financial issue.
Um I will say that residency
requirements are problematic and while I
understand the argument to say that um
that because this is psilocybin Congress
didn't contemplate anything in the way
of interstate commerce and therefore the
dormant commerce clause doesn't apply.
Um that's not sort of the majority
opinion right now. There's one opinion
that came out very recently in the Ninth
Circuit that says that um I would just
say the Ninth Circuit is the most
overturned circuit in the United States.
I think something like 93% of their
cases that go before the US Supreme
Court get overturned. Um so I don't put
a lot of stock in it. Of course, we're
in the 10th Circuit. There have been a
couple of other circuits that have
considered the question in the context
of medical cannabis programs, the first
circuit and second circuit. Um, and they
both went the other way. And I would
just add also that I don't think it's
just a dormant commerce issue. Um, so if
if the dormant commerce clause applies,
then you have to apply strict scrutiny
and there's no way that it's going to
survive strict scrutiny. So I I
understand the the emphasis on saying
dormant commerce doesn't apply. But I
think what is likely to happen now in
the Ninth Circuit is that you're going
to see a lot of case law where instead
of arguing about dormant commerce,
they're going to be arguing about the
privileges and immunities clause. And
you're going to see people who are
negatively impacted by this suing the
state for monetary damages
uh and perhaps successfully um under the
privileges and immunities clause. um you
know that that's something that you can
sue over in a 1983 suit and potentially
get monetary damages over and of course
that sets I can't recall the exact
standard but it's something like a
substantial justification and you know
the problem that you run into with these
types of residency requirements is that
at best they're only kind of loosely
connected to what you're trying to
achieve. So, for example, I'm a New
Mexico resident.
Um,
so I would be permitted to grow
psilocybin in the state if there was a
residency requirement. Do I not have the
same incentive to grow mushrooms in to
grow psilocybin in Colorado and bring it
across state lines to invert? I do. I
have the same incentive. Arguably, I
have less in the way of an option
because maybe I don't live in Colorado.
But if I'm a New Mexico resident, does
that mean that I don't have a growth
facility in Colorado? No, it doesn't.
And so I think that's the real problem
that you have. And that's why you can't
really you can't satisfy a higher level
of scrutiny on this. Um maybe you can
get past rational basis but certainly
not strict scrutiny which in this case
would ask is your requirement narrowly
tailored to achieve a legitimate state
interest. We can't meet that standard
and for privileges and immunities you'd
have to meet a standard of a substantial
justification. I don't think we can meet
that standard either. So, while I
understand I mean it's perfectly fine if
the advisory board makes a
recommendation in favor of this and and
it's within your discretion to do so,
ultimately the department of health is
going to have to make a decision um
after the rule hearing. Of course, we'll
receive public comment on it, but I
think at least as far as a residency
requirement goes, it's probably not
going to happen.
>> Thank you, Chris.
uh Desb
um
illegalities aside and and laws etc and
restrictions, I'm just thinking that
this could potentially be a part of the
access portion
um and what that is specifically for New
Mexicans just from you know a more
broader um point advantage point. So it
it would still fall under like us having
a recommendation and not not sidest
stepping it.
>> Thank you. And yes, again, um I
understand there's legal scrutiny on
this, but I propose that we still make
this recommendation and allow that
conversation to continue between the
legal team with the Department of Health
and and the Micology Guild.
>> Any other questions?
All right. Um,
at this time, can we take a look at the
predatory f I'm getting an echo. Can
somebody mute, please?
Um, can we take a look at the predatory
uh
financing language, Dominic?
>> Yes, let me bring that on up. Please
give me a moment. Um, it's actually in a
separate document. Um what essentially
we had been looking at was this was one
of the questions that was raised that uh
was actually a little bit more um
concerning even than with regard to um
this conversation about the financial
ownership within New Mexico. Um, and let
me pull up. Um, uh, and I will say Chris
Woodward was, uh, very good about
creating some language with the help of
some of the folks that we had, uh, met
with, uh, including, uh, Victoria
Civotanovich,
uh, who joined with us in that. Um, and
so this is a little bit lengthy and, um,
so I'm going to
do this. So, give me just a moment
everyone. My my apologies. I'm uh again,
like I said, I'm pulling it out of
another document. There are some
notations in here just because the
document itself uh as we're that Chris
had done has his notes in it. Um but
here we go. Um, and so essentially what
this does is it says that a permittee
shall comply with all applicable state,
tribal, and local laws, regulations, and
ordinances, including requirements
concerning agriculture, environmental
health, building and occupancy, fire
safety, zoning, and worker safety. Dual
ownership prohibited. A person who holds
an ownership interest in a permit shall
not hold an ownership interest in any
other permit.
Permits non-transferable. Permit shall
not be transferred by assignment or
otherwise to another person. A permit
that is transferred to another person
shall be invalid. An applicant or
permittee shall not convey actual
control of the applicant or permittee to
another person through the use of a
management consulting or intellectual
property agreement or by any other
means. Nominee straw and proxy ownership
prohibited.
Um if any ownership interest in the
permit is not is nominal or without the
benefits and risks of genuine ownership
or control and then record of financial
interests. Permites shall create and
maintain complete lists of all
individuals and legal entities that hold
a financial interest in the permittee or
the operations of the permittee
including contact information for each
individual or entity and a description
of their financial interest. Applicants
and permittes shall provide the
information required by this section to
the department within 15 calendar days
of the department's written request for
such information. If a legal entity
holds a financial interest in the
permittee or the permittes operations
within the medical psilocybin program,
the following individuals within the
legal entity shall be deemed to also
hold a financial interest. A for limited
partnerships, each general partner in
the limited partnership. B for limited
liability companies, each manager and
managing member of the limited liability
company. C for not for forprofit
corporations, each principal officer of
the corporation. And D for nonprofit
entities, each principal officer of the
entity.
Um, and then, uh, Chris, do you Chris
Woodward, do you mind, um, just, uh,
explaining a little bit what nominee and
straw proxy ownership is? Uh,
>> yeah. I mean, I think just to give an
example, um, and this this came up in
our conversation, uh, with Chris and
Victoria the other day as well, and it
sort of prompted some further review.
Some of the language that that, um,
we've we've come up with so far. what
Dominic was just describing, some of
that language is taken from what
Victoria sent us. Um, some of it is
taken from other states. So, I think
some of that is from Maryland and some
of it may be from Missouri. But on the
subject of of proxy arrangements, straw
straw ownership issues,
um this was something that you would see
sometimes in the medical cannabis
context. Um where uh you would have
people who would sort of pretend to be
the owner, but they're not really the
owner. And the people who are actually
controlling things um are other folks.
And so you get into issues there where
um for one thing, you just don't really
know who's who's controlling the entity.
Um so that that in essence is what
that's trying to prohibit. The kinds of
um the kinds of management arrangements.
It was very um common in the medical
cannabis program for these producers and
um other licensed entities to have what
they called management agreements where
um they would enter into they would they
would officially be the the owner of an
entity but they would into a contract
with someone else uh where they
basically just agreed to do everything
that that other person said to do. Um
which for obvious reasons is really
problematic. So the language that
Dominic just described would would
address that.
>> Thank you, Chris. And thank you,
Dominic. And I just wanted to be clear
that the um predatory financial language
did not come through the committee. That
was a um kind of a side meeting that uh
we were continuing the discussion about
the sunset clause through. show.
>> Um, Dominic, if if I may. So, on on the
subject of predatory financing, um,
the language that that Dominic just read
off doesn't really address like loans
and I mean, at least not in terms of I
know what what Victoria had proposed was
more along the lines of the agency
almost like reviewing loans and and
approving loans and that sort of thing.
Um, at this point we're not proposing
that. Um, and I think the concern there,
and Dominic feel free to jump in on
this, but I think the concern there is
that it would be uh a lot of work for
the program and kind of overbearing as
well. And I think maybe more to sort of
the the core issue if if your concern is
that the use of predatory loans
um if if if at the end of the line the
issue is that by someone using a
predatory loan they will eventually be
able to acquire ownership of the entity.
Um then perhaps it's not as critical to
review all of the loans. um if so long
as you have provisions such as what
Dominic just described where you you're
basically saying you just cannot
transfer a permit, you can't transfer
ownership presumably with a requirement
like that in place in the law. Uh
lenders are not going to uh lend you
money on the on the basis that
eventually ownership will transfer to
them because it will be clear that
ownership cannot transfer to them. So, I
I hope that explains that, but um again,
it's it's kind of an ongoing process and
I as the department receives more
comments about this um maybe there will
be some some tweaks to that. I'm not
sure.
>> Thank you, Chris.
>> All right. Are there any other questions
or comments?
Excellent. Then I'll go ahead and I'll
turn it back over to Ian.
>> Perfect. Thank you guys. Um,
so we have two options. We can defer to
the voting on this until the next
meeting and allow us to hear public
comment first or we can vote on it now.
What is whatever the board members
feeling like
Ian, if I may, I would recommend voting
on this today. Um, even if you do decide
to hear public comment, I think there's
been opportunity for people to comment
on it at this time. And and just as a
note, when the final regulations are
actually uh created and submitted, there
is a 30-day period where they are open
for public comment. So, even here at the
board, it is not the last time that
they, you know, that the that that
there's voting or comment allowed, so to
speak. Does that make sense?
>> Perfect. Uh and then Chris had his hand
up.
I think Dominic answered most of what I
was going to say. And uh
>> All right, then we will go ahead and
move to a vote. If you want to pull up
the hand raising screen for me.
All right.
So
all right. So what I will go ahead and
do is if the board members are in
support of passing the propagation
outline with the definition stried out,
please raise your hand at this time.
of those attending, there is unanimous
consent to adopt. Um,
perfect.
If you could all put your hands down
ceremonially, if there's anyone in
negation, please raise your hand at this
time.
Perfect. The motion is adopted. The
propagation outline is adopted with the
definition stried out. All righty. So,
that looks like that was what we had on
the agenda today. Is there any other
business you feel we need to get to
before we turn to public comment?
>> All right, I will turn it over to uh
>> just do we know where the next meeting
is?
>> You are right. We need to set the next
meeting. Thank you so much for that
reminder. Um so we can do in another
month if you guys want. We could do
March 20th or 27th if you wanted to do
another Friday, but when works best for
y'all.
>> The 20th in the morning works for me.
>> Like 9:00 a.m. or earlier?
>> Uh either way. Uh, then let's do the
20th at 9:00 a.m.
Everyone good with that? No objections.
Cool.
2026.
Perfect. All right. Oh, Chris has his
hand up.
>> Yeah. So, I I do have a question for the
board. What would you like the
propagation committee to work on next?
Um, I have two more meetings set up. I
kind of expected or uh there that parts
of this may have gotten kicked back to
committee, but seeing that this has been
adopted now, um, what what questions do
you all have for the propagation
committee?
>> Uh, Chris, Ian, if you're okay. I I
actually have some information on that.
So, um Chris, uh what we are hoping is
that by the time the next meeting is
happening that we will actually have
some drafts of the regulations and so I
would say that those meetings can
actually be utilized to look at the
drafts that we have created as a
department and help us uh with regard to
that.
>> That sounds good. Are there any other
questions the board would like uh the
propagation committee to answer?
>> Go ahead, Despa.
>> I just had a question for Dominic.
>> Sure. Oh, so I just was wanted to know
if we had an update on the equity fund
uh result of that in the legislation and
then also the tribal liaison and then it
looks like some people are asking about
uh when the next committee meetings or
where to find that um on the website.
>> Sure. Yeah. So, uh I'd actually put
earlier in the chat where all of the
committee meetings are. We have both the
website and we have the links for the
meetings are earlier in the chat. We'll
duplicate that here in just a minute. Um
and uh as far as for the equity fund,
thank you Despa. Um we usually wait
until the governor has signed, but what
essentially has happened is uh the
legislature did pass um $630,000
allocated towards the equity fund. Um
and then and Larry, correct me if I'm
incorrect on this, but I believe it was
300,000 to UNM directly for research. Is
that is that correct, Larry?
>> Excuse me. Dom, that that's correct.
It's in a couple of different batches,
but it amounts to 300. And we talked
it's for end of life research.
>> Yes. And so so both of those are now um
have moved forward to the governor's
desk for signature. And so once we have
that signature, then uh we'll see what
happens. Uh of course, always as a
reminder, the governor does have the
ability to veto. um which is why we
usually don't announce that until after
uh signature. Um uh but in any case that
is there and that is going to be
something that especially for the
committee that you're chairing Despa is
going to be very important as we start
looking at what are going to be the
requirements uh for people to be
eligible for some of the funds out of
that and I think that's going to be a
fantastic task quite frankly and one
that we're very happy and looking
forward to tackle.
Oh, and uh some of my team have actually
already put in the uh the links within
the chat for all of the upcoming
meetings
>> and then um yeah, so we're imagining um
MLG signing
off on that.
>> I I do not speak for the governor.
However, what I can say is I do know the
bill is has already been submitted.
What's up?
All right.
With no other board members with
questions, I think I'll turn it back to
you, Dom, for
public comment.
>> Okay. And so at this time, if there are
any members of the public who are
interested in speaking, and I do already
see uh at least one hand, um the
information on how to raise your hand is
here on the screen. I will be putting it
into the chat in just a minute. Um and
then once you are called on, uh then you
can go ahead and unmute yourself and uh
you may speak. So Adrien, I believe you
are handling that aspect.
Thank you very much, Dominic. You are
correct. First up to speak is job or
job. My apologies for if I mispronounce
that. Your microphone credentials have
been enabled. Go ahead and unmute
yourself, please.
>> Yeah, I I got here late, so I do
apologize. Um I have just have a couple
of questions. um would it make sense to
um facilitate
u a transportation service with the
federal government that they would
accept and that would resolve all
transportation issues?
Um the second question is do you guys
monitor uh forever chemicals in the
water that is added to the cycllin?
And the last question is um I'm actually
looking to get into
participating in the medical research as
a patient.
And those are my three questions.
Thank you.
Next up is Jeremy. Jeremy, I've enabled
your microphone. Please unmute yourself.
Hello everybody. Uh my name is Jeremy.
Um I appreciate you guys uh giving me a
chance to speak. I just wanted to
elaborate on uh the full fruitruing body
advantages that you guys will be
focusing on. Um you know basically when
you're dealing with full body fruing um
or full fruitruing body rather um you
are essentially getting the highest
diversity of bioactive compounds.
Um those fruing bodies
typically contain the full spectrum of
secondary metabolites. Um examples of
those would be your various alkyoids, uh
turpenoids, etc. Um some compounds that
are only expressed or maximized during
fruing versus the vegetative phase. So I
just wanted to add that um you know your
vegetative phase was mentioned as
mycelio biomass. Um and this also I
believe makes for clear labeling. You
know you can label you know something
that's 100% fruing body. So kudos to you
guys for for that you know. Um a
downside of grain grown mycelium you
know is that it can be up to 70% starch.
um if it's not separated or f fermented
in a clean manner. So residual starch as
many of us know that are in the
microcology community um is a readily
available sugar source and it you know
feeds bacteria and encourages yeast and
mold growth undesirabs you know. So, um,
another thing I I wanted to ask, I guess
this question would be for Chris, um,
you know, where are you guys at with
insight for producers on, uh, lab
procedure, you know, when it comes to
sterilization,
um, aseptic technique and stuff like
that? Um, are there going to be, you
know, MSDS sheets available for
employees to protect employees, um,
things of that nature? Because, you
know, those of us that do lab work on a
reg on a regular basis, you know, we're
we're in constant contact with corrosive
stuff, you know, um we're using bleach,
we're using uh you know, parasitic acid,
um 70% ISO, things of that manner. So, I
just kind of wanted to know where you
guys were at with that. Thanks.
>> Thank you.
And just a friendly reminder, if anyone
else wishes to make public comment on
the Microsoft Teams app, there is the
raise hand or uh the raise icon with the
hand, excuse me, and you can click or
tap on that. So that way then it'll the
software will move you up so that way we
can allow your credentials to speak.
And if you are uh joining through a
phone, it is star five to raise or lower
your hand. And currently because there
is no hands up at this time, I will pass
it grace back off to either Ian or
Dominic.
Alrighty. Well, if given that there's a
little under 10 minutes left and um we
have no more public comment, I say we go
ahead and adjourn. Thank you guys all so
much for coming. I really appreciate all
of your time and help today and I wish
you all the best weekend.
On behalf of the department, thank you
everybody for participating and for all
the hard work that has gone into
everything so far and uh looking forward
to the next sets of committee meetings
and again we have put those meetings in
the chat and uh so if anyone is
interested you can also find them and
updated meetings in in the meanwhile
between now and the next board meeting.
We do put those on the website um on the
psilocybin uh advisory board meeting
page and so that people can actually
come and register and participate in all
of the various aspects of the
committees.
Thank you everybody. Hope everybody has
a wonderful Friday. And don't forget if
you are interested this afternoon is the
dosage administration and clinical
practice meeting starting at 100 am.